Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Semester: III Subject: Mathematics – III Code: 324351(14) Total Theory Periods:                     40    Total Tutorial Periods: 10 Class Tests: Two (Minimum) Assignments: Two (Minimum) ESE Duration: Three Hours Maximum Marks: 80 Minimum Marks: 28 Course Objectives: 1. To make the students understand that Fourier series analysis is powerful methods where the formulas are integrals and to have knowledge of expanding periodic functions that explore variety of applications of Fourier series. 2. To provide knowledge of Laplace transform of elementary functions including its properties and applications to solve ordinary differential equations. 3. To have thorough knowledge of partial differential equations which arise in mathematical descriptions of situations in engineering. 4. To provide a sound background of complex analysis to perform thorough investigation of major theorems of complex analysis and to apply these ideas to a wide range of problems those include the evaluation of both complex line integrals and real integrals. 5. Know the concepts of Z-transforms, its definition, region of convergence and apply its most frequently occurring properties.
UNIT- I Fourier series: Euler’s Formula, Functions having points of discontinuity, Change of interval, Even & Odd functions, half range series, Harmonic analysis. UNIT-II Laplace transform : Definition, Transform of elementary functions, Properties of Laplace transform, Transform of derivatives & integrals, Multiplication by tn, Division by t, Evaluation of integrals, Inverse Laplace Transform, Convolution theorem, Unit step function, Unit impulse function, Periodic function, Application to solution of ordinary differential equations. UNIT- III Partial differential equation: Formation, Solution by direct integration method, Linear equation of first order, Homogeneous linear equation with constant coefficients, Non-homogeneous linear equations, Method of separation of variables. UNIT-IV Complex variables: Derivative, Cauchy-Riemann equations, Analytic functions, Harmonic functions, Flow problems, Complex integration, Cauchy theorem, Cauchy integral formula, Taylor& Laurent series, Singularity, Residue and Evaluation of real definite integrals. UNIT-V Z-transform: Definition, Properties, Initial value & final value theorems, Inverse Z-transform, Convolution theorem, Partial fraction, Residue method & Applications to solution of difference equations.
Text Books: 1. “Higher Engg. Mathematics”, Dr. B.S. Grewal– Khanna Publishers. 2. “Advanced Engg. Mathematics” , Erwin Kreyszig – John Wiley & Sons.
Reference Books: 1. “Advanced Engg. Mathematics”, R.K. Jain and S.R.K. Iyengar – Narosa Publishing House. 2. “Applied Mathematics”, P.N.Wartikar& J.N. Wartikar. Vol-II Pune VidyarthiGrihaPrakashan,Pune. 3. “Applied Mathematics for Engineers & Physicists”, Louis A. Pipes- TMH.
Course outcomes: After studying the contents of the syllabus in detail the3 students will be able to: 1. Define Fourier series including half-range series , harmonic analysis and variety of applications 2. Define (mathematically) unit step unit impulse, Laplace transform its properties, inverse and applications to solve ordinary differential equations. 3. Solve difficult problems using theorems of complex analysis and apply residue theorem to evaluate real integrals. 4. Form and solve by direct integration methods linear equations of first order including homogenous and non homogenous, linear equations and also method of separation of variables. 5. Know the definition of Z-transform; calculate Z-transform of some elementary signals, convolution product, formulation of corresponding convolution theorem and its applications to solve difference equations.’
Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Semester: III Subject: Electrical Machines I Code: 324352(24) Total Theory Periods:                     40    Total Tutorial Periods: 10 Class Tests: Two (Minimum) Assignments: Two (Minimum) ESE Duration: Three Hours Maximum Marks: 80 Minimum Marks: 28 Course Objectives:
The objective of this course is to expose the studentson basic knowledge of construction and working of various transformers their equivalent circuit, parameter determination and applications. This course also provides the knowledge of direct current electrical machines, its operational constraints, starting mechanisms, conventional speed control methods, various tests and applications.
UNIT- I Single Phase Transformer: Introduction, Constructional features of a transformer, core and shell type, working principle of a transformer, EMF equation, Ideal transformer, Actual transformer on no-load and on load, phasor diagram (no load, lagging and leading power factor), Equivalent circuit, per unit representation, Voltage regulation of a transformer, Losses in a transformer, Open circuit and short circuit test, Efficiency, condition for maximum efficiency.
UNIT-II Single Phase Transformer and Auto-transformer:Back-to-Back test, power and distribution transformer, All-day efficiency, Polarity test, separation of losses, auto-transformer, its equivalent circuit and phasor diagram, its comparison with two winding transformer, conversion from auto- transformer to two winding transformer and vice versa, Parallel operation of single-phase transformer (equal and unequal voltage ratios), excitation phenomenon in transformers.
UNIT- III Three Phase Transformer: Three-phase transformers, constructional details (three and five limb), Bank of three single phase units, three phase single unit transformer, different connections and vector groups, calculation of efficiency and regulation, Parallel operation of three-phase transformer, Scott connection, open delta, Equivalent circuit of three winding transformer and its parameter determination (elementary  only).
UNIT-IV DC Machine –I:Electromagnetic principle of DC machine, BLV and BLI concept, constructional details, production of voltage and torque, classification of DC machine, armature reaction and its effect, methods to reduce armature reaction, commutation, methods of improving commutation, effect of brush shift, Operating characteristics of DC separately excited, series and shunt (condition of self excitation, critical speed and critical resistance) generator.
UNIT-V DC Machine –II:Electrical and mechanical characteristics of DC motor, starters for shunt motors- two point, three point and four point starter, speed control of DC motors- armature and field control method, losses in DC machines, efficiency and condition for maximum efficiency, Testing of DC machines- Swinburne’s test and Regenerative test(Study only).
Text Books: 1. Nagrath& Kothari, “Electric Machines”, TMH Publications, 2. B. R, Gupta, “Electrical machines”, New Age International 3. P. S. Bimbhra, “Electrical Machinery”, Khanna Publishers
Reference Books: 1. J. B. Gupta, “Theory & Performance of Electrical Machines”, S. K. Kataria & Sons 2. Ashfaq Hussain, “Electric Machines”, Dhanpat Rai Publication 3. Samarjeet Ghosh, “Electrical Machines”, PHI Publications 4. P.K. Mukherjee & S. Chakravarti “Electric Machines”, Dhanpat Rai Publication,
Course outcomes: 1. Understand the fundamentals and working of transformers 2. Draw the equivalent circuit diagrams of various transformers 3. Analyse the load profile, voltage regulations and efficiency under various operating conditions 4. Understand the working principle and construction of direct current machines 5. Understand the needs and requirements of various types of d.c. machine operations like starting, speed control, tests etc.
Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Semester: III Subject: Basic Electronics Code: 324353(25) Total Theory Periods:                     40    Total Tutorial Periods: 10 Class Tests: Two (Minimum) Assignments: Two (Minimum) ESE Duration: Three Hours Maximum Marks: 80 Minimum Marks: 28 Course Objectives: 1. To understand the basic concept electronics devices their property, behavior and application.as. 2. To understand the concept of waves shaping circuit and constant power supply. 3. To understand the concept of solid state rectifiers. 4. Application of transistor as an amplifier and switch. 5. To learn the concept of positive and negative feedback in amplifier. 6. Gain experience in the designing of an electronics circuit.
UNIT- I Introduction: Transport Phenomena in semiconductor, Formation of P-N Junction, Properties of P-N Junction, P-N Junction Diodes; Semiconductor Diodes, V-I Characteristics, Effect of Temperature on V-I Characteristics, Ideal Diode, Diode equation, Diode Resistance, Diode Capacitance: Transition and Diffusion Capacitance.
UNIT-II Rectifying circuits and DC Power Supplies: Load line analysis of diode circuit, Half wave rectifier: Voltage regulation, Ripple factor, ratio of rectification, Transformer Utilization factor. Full wave rectifier, Bridge rectifier, Filter circuits for power supply: Inductor filter, Capacitor filter, LC filter, Multiple LC filter, CLC or filter. Zener diode: Break down mechanism, Characteristics, Specifications, Voltage regulator circuit using zener diode.
UNIT- III Transistor: Introduction, Construction, Types: npn and pnp, Current components. Transistor as an amplifier, Transistor Characteristics, Transistor Circuit Configuration: Common Base (CB) Configuration, Common Emitter (CE) Configuration, Common Collector Configuration (CC), Early Effect. Ebers-Moll Model, Maximum Voltage ratings.
UNIT-IV Field Effect Transistor (FET): Introduction, Construction, Operation, V-I Characteristics, Transfer Characteristics, Drain Characteristics, Metal Oxide Semiconductor Field Effect Transistor (MOSFET): Introduction, Construction, Operation and characteristics, Depletion MOSFET, Enhancement MOSFET.
UNIT-V Passive Clipper and Clamper Circuits: classification of series and parallel clipper and clamper circuits, biased and unbiased clipper and clamper circuits, R-C low pass and high pass circuits. Oscillator: Sinusoidal oscillator, phase shift oscillators, Wien Bridge oscillator, Resonant circuit oscillators: General form of Oscillator Configuration- LC Colpitts and LC Hartley, Crystal oscillator. (Elementary treatment of BJT based oscillators only)
Text Books: 1. Integrated Electronics: Analog & Digital Circuit Systems – Jacob Millman&Halkias, TMH. 2. Electronic Devices and Circuit Theory – Boylestad&Nashelsky, 8th Ed. PHI. Reference Books: 1. “Electronic Devices & Circuit Analysis” – K. Lal Kishore, BS Publications 2. “Principle of electronics devices” - Flyod, Pearson Publication. 3. “Electronic Devices & Circuits”; I.J.Nagrath, PHI publications 4. “Electronic Devices & Circuits” – Allen Mottershead, PHI Learning.
Course outcomes: 1. Student can predict and design rectifiers and filters as per circuit requirement. 2. Learn to design transistor biasing circuit and calculating its stability. 3. Student can apply the concept of feedback in amplifier circuit. 4. Learn to design oscillator of desired frequency. 5. Gain experience in the problem finding and trouble shooting in electronics circuits consisting of diodes and transistors.
Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Semester: III Subject: Electric Circuits Code: 324354(25) Total Theory Periods:                     40    Total Tutorial Periods: 10 Class Tests: Two (Minimum) Assignments: Two (Minimum) ESE Duration: Three Hours Maximum Marks: 80 Minimum Marks: 28 Course Objectives: 1. To provide knowledge of Basic Electric Circuit Concepts. 2. To provide the concept of conversion of electrical circuits to graphs for determination of current and voltages. 3. To provide Knowledge of various theorems and its applications to circuits. 4. To give the knowledge of analysis of network reduction and calculation of various parameters. 5. To know the basic concepts of coupled circuits and network performance under resonance condition. 6. To provide knowledge of threephase balanced and unbalanced Poly phase Circuits and measurement of three phase power. 7. To provide the concept of non-sinusoidal waveforms and its impact on electrical circuits
UNIT- I Development of Circuit Concepts: The relationship of field and circuit concept for parameters of circuit elements, active and passive elements: resistance, inductance and capacitance, voltage and current sources, duality of simple circuit, normalizing factor, Network topology: graph, tree, branch link, tie-set, cut-set, incidence matrix, loop and nodal analysis, equilibrium equations (conductively coupled circuit only). UNIT-II Network Solution And Reduction: Solution of network equation of determination method of network reductions, nodal analysis, mesh analysis, super node, super mesh, star-delta transformation, Superposition theorem, Reciprocity theorem, Thevenin’s theorem, Norton’s theorem, Maximum power transfer theorem, Millman’s theorem (independent & dependent sources). UNIT- III Magnetic coupled circuits and Resonance: Electrostatic and electromagnetic coupling, self-inductance, mutual inductance, coupling coefficient, complete network solution with conductive and inductive coupling, Series and parallel resonance, quality factor, bandwidth, selectivity, half power frequencies, locus diagram of simple series and parallel circuits. UNIT-IV Poly Phase Circuits: Examples of two, three, four-loop circuits in poly phase circuit and their solutions, unbalanced poly phase circuits, determination of phase sequence, star/delta connections, and power measurement in poly phase circuits. UNIT-V Non-sinusoidal Ideal Wave Forms: Common non-sinusoidal waveforms, Fourier series, analytical evaluation of Fourier coefficients, exponential form of Fourier series, frequency spectra of periodic waveforms, effective value and equivalent power factor, solution of circuits with non sinusoidal currents and voltages, harmonic resonance in single phase circuits. Text Books: 1. “Fundamentals of Electric Circuits” Alexander &Sadiku, TMH Publications. 2. “Electrical Circuits and networks”, K. Sureshkumar, Pearson Education/, First Edition
Reference Books: 1. “Circuit Analysis Theory and Practice”, Allan H. Robbins and Wilhelm C. Miller,   Cengage Learning. 2. “Electric Circuit Analysis”, Hayt, Kemmerly, Durbin, TMH Publications 3. “Engineering Network Analysis and Filter Design”, Gopal G. Bhise, Prem R. Chandra, Durgesh C. Kulshreshtha, Umesh Publications. 4. “Network Analysis & Synthesis”, D. Roy Choudhary, New Age International publications.
Course outcomes: 1. Students will learn about the different types of electrical sources and networks 2. Students will have knowledge of converting a electrical circuit into graph and will be able to analyze the circuit graphically. 3. Student will analyse circuits with ideal, independent, and controlled voltage and current sources 4. Student will be able to find out current through or voltage across any branch of a given Electrical network using theorems. 5. Students will learn about series and parallel resonance conditions in series and parallel circuits and its impact on network voltage and current magnitudes. 6. Students will have knowledge of balanced and unbalanced poly phase circuits. 7. Students will be able to analyze the behavior of non-sinusoidal waveforms
Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Electronics Semester: III Subject: Electrical Engineering Materials Code: 324355(24) Total Theory Periods:                     40    Total Tutorial Periods: 10 Class Tests: Two (Minimum) Assignments: Two (Minimum) ESE Duration: Three Hours Maximum Marks: 80 Minimum Marks: 28 Course Objectives: 1. To provide knowledge Conductor. 2. To provide the concept of semi-conductor material 3. To provide Knowledge of Dielectrics and Insulators. 4. To give the knowledge of Magnetic Materials. 5. To know the basic concepts of Optical Properties of Solids.
UNIT- I Conductors: Classification: High conductivity, high resistivity materials, fundamental requirements of high conductivity materials and high resistivity materials, motion of electron in metals, properties and application of high conductivity(copper, aluminium, bronze & brass) & high resistivity(constanton,nichrome,carbon & platinum) materials,Electrical contact materials, super-conductors  and their applications.
UNIT-II Semi-Conductors: General concepts, energy bands, types of semiconductors, Fermi Dirac distribution, intrinsic Semi-conductors, extrinsic Semi-conductors, hall effect, drift, mobility, diffusion in Semiconductors, Semiconductors and their applications.
UNIT- III Dielectrics And Insulators: Properties of gaseous, liquid and solid dielectric, dielectric as a field medium, electric conduction in gaseous, liquid and solid dielectric, breakdown in dielectric materials, mechanical and electrical properties of dielectric materials, effect of temperature on dielectric materials, polarization, loss angle and dielectric loss, petroleum based insulating oils, transformer oil, capacitor oils, properties, solid electrical insulating materials, fibrous, paper boards, yarns, cloth tapes, sleeving wood, impregnation, plastics, filling and bounding materials, fibrous, film, mica, rubber, mica based materials, ceramic materials, classification of insulation ( solid) and application in AC and DC machines.
UNIT-IV Magnetic Materials: Soft and hard magnetic materials, diamagnetic, paramagnetic and ferromagnetic materials, electric steel, cold rolled grain oriented silicon steel, silicon steel, hot rolled silicon steel sheet, hystersis loop, hystersis loss, magnetic susceptibility, coercive force, curie temperature, magneto-striction, Ferro-electric materials, piezo-electric materials & their properties.
UNIT-V Optical Properties of Solids: Photo emission, photo emissive materials, electro luminescence junction diode, photo emitters, photo resistors, injunction lasers, optical properties of semiconductors, application of photo sensitive materials (CRT, Tube light, photo panels etc.). Text Books: 1. “Electrical Engineering Materials”,Dekker,PHI Publications. 2. “Electrical Engineering Materials”, Indulkar,S.Chand Publications.
Reference Books: 1. “Electrical Engineering Materials”, B.M.Tareev 2. “A course in electrical engineering materials”, S.P.Seth, Dhanpat Rai Publication. 3. “Electrical Engineering Materials”, R.K.Rajput, Laxmi Publications. 4. "Substation Design and Control" by Gupta &Satnam
Course outcomes: 1. Understand the properties of conductors. 2. Understand the properties of semiconductor. 3. Understand the properties of insulator 4. Students will have knowledge of Magnetic material. 5. Students will be able to know the Optical Properties of Solids
Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Semester: III Subject: Electrical Power Generation Code: 324356(24) Total Theory Periods:                     40    Total Tutorial Periods: 10 Class Tests: Two (Minimum) Assignments: Two (Minimum) ESE Duration: Three Hours Maximum Marks: 80 Minimum Marks: 28 Course Objectives: 1. To provide the students with a broad understanding of predictions of different load demands of the consumers. 2. Student will understand the layout diagrams of power system by drawing the typical load curves 3. To provide the students with a broad understanding of electricity generation. 4. Students will understand the operation and major components ofelectric generating plants. 5. Students will have a basic understanding of conversion of coal, oil, gas ,nuclear, hydro, solar,   geothermal, etc. energy to electrical energy.
UNIT- I Introduction: Sources of energy, comparison of sources of energy, Growth of power generation in India, need for nonconventional energy sources Prediction of Load: Definition of connected load, maximum load, maximum demand, demand factor, load factor, diversity factor, plant capacity factor, plant utilization factor, load duration curve, mass curve. Calculation based on above factors.
UNIT-II Thermal Power generation : Main parts and working of thermal power station, main features of boilers, steam turbines, Auxiliaries, coal preparation , Ash Handling and layout of thermal power station.
UNIT- III Hydro Power Stations: Hydrology, hydrographs, flow duration & mass curve, main types of dams, turbines & generators, pumped storage plant. Nuclear power Generation:  Principles of nuclear power generation, main parts of nuclear power plants, types of reactors, nuclear waste hazards & disposal.
UNIT-IV Solar Energy:solar radiation, solar collectors , conversion of solar energy in to electrical energy , solar water heater ,solar hydrogen energy cycle. Wind energy: wind power plants: principles of wind power generation , wind turbine operation & control.
UNIT-V MHD Generation: principle of MHD generation, MHD cycles & working fluids, open cycles & closed cycle MHD system, merits &demerits. Other methods of power generation: Tidal power generation ocean Thermal energy, geothermal power generation, Biomass applications in power generation, use of different types of generation for base loads/peak loads. Text Books: 1. Generation of electrical energy by BR Gupta, S. Chand Publications. 2. Generation & Economic consideration by JB Gupta,SK kataria  publications 3. Nonconventional Energy Sources by G D Rai, Khanna Publications Reference Books: 1. A Course in Electrical Power by JB Gupta, S K Kataria Publications. 2. A Course in Electrical Power by Chakravoarty,SoniGupta, Bhatnagar – DhanpatRaiPublications. 3. Elements of Power Station Design by M.V.Deshpande, PHI publications. Course outcomes: 1. Students must apply both mathematics and chemistry to understand and solve problems in this  course. 2. Students perform design type analyses and solve engineering problems. 3. There are many aspects of contemporary issues addressed in this course, especially with regard to power plant environmental and sitting issues. 4. Students will able to generate economic dispatch between generating units. 5. Students will have a basic understanding of conversion of coal, oil, gas, nuclear, hydro, solar, geothermal, etc. energy to electrical energy. 6. An ability to apply a multi-disciplinary approach to conceive, plan, design, and implementsolutions to electrical engineering problems in the field of energy and sustainability. 7. Successfully apply advanced concepts of electrical power engineering    to the analysis, design and development of electric systems, components, equipments or applications to meet desired needs of society professionally and ethically. 8. Use advanced techniques, skills, and modern scientific and engineering software tools for professional practice
Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Semester: III Subject: Electrical Machines-I Lab Code: 324361(24) Total Lab Periods:                     36 Batch Size: 30 Maximum Marks: 40 Minimum Marks: 20
List of Experiments: (At leastTen experiments are to be performed by each student) 1. To determine the equivalent circuit parameters of a single phase transformer. 2. To determine the voltage regulation of a single phase transformer operating at lagging and upf condition. 3. To determine the  efficiency of a single phase transformer  under different loading condition  4. To perform the tests required for parallel operation of transformers. 5. To perform parallel operation of two single phase transformer. 6. To study the voltage/current ratios for different types of three phase transformer connection. 7. To perform Back to Back test on two single phase transformer. 8. To perform 3-phase to 2- phase conversion (Scott connection) 9. To study the various routine tests performed on three phase transformers as per IS code. 10. To determine the armature & field winding resistance of D.C machine by voltmeter/ammeter method. 11. To determine the magnetization or Open circuit characteristics of a D.C machine 12. To perform load test on D.C shunt generator. 13. To perform Swinburne’s test a D.C machine & calculate its efficiency at full load operating condition. 14. To study three point and four point motor starters and observe its impact on the motor staring current. 15. Speed control of D.C shunt motor by (a) Varying field current with armature voltage kept constant; (b) Varying armature voltage with field current kept constant. 16. To study the reversal of D.C shunts motor.
Equipment/Machines/Instruments/Tools/Software Required:
Single Phase Transformer, Three Phase Transformer, Three Phase Auto Transformer, DC Shunt Generator Set, DC Shunt Motor, DC series Motor, Ammeters (AC & DC), Voltmeter (AC & DC), Wattmeter, Tachometer
Recommended Book: Laboratory courses in electrical engineering by S.G. Tarnekar& P.K. Kharbanda
Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Semester: III Subject: Basic Electronics Laboratory Code: 324362(24) Total Lab Periods:                     36 Batch Size: 30 Maximum Marks: 40 Minimum Marks: 20
List of Experiments: (At leastTen experiments are to be performed by each student) 1. To study the operation of CRO and DSO (Digital oscilloscope). 2. To draw the characteristics of a semi-conductor diode and to find cut-in voltage, reverse resistance, static resistance and dynamic resistance. 3. To draw the characteristics of a zener diode. 4. To design a half wave rectifier and to determine its efficiency and ripple factor. 5. To design a-full wave rectifier and determine the ripple factor and efficiency with & without filter. 6. To design and analysis of biased and unbiased Clamper circuit. 7. To design and analyze biased and unbiased series Clipper. 8. To design and analyze biased and unbiased parallel Clipper. 9. To draw the characteristics of CB configuration of a transistor amplifier. 10. To draw the characteristics of CC configuration of a transistor amplifier. 11. To design a Zener regulator circuit and to find the regulation characteristics. 12. To draw the load line of a transistor amplifier under CE configuration. 13. To draw the characteristics of FET 14. To study Wein Bridge Oscillator & R-C phase shift oscillator. 15. To design the positive voltage regulator.
Equipment/Machines/Instruments/Tools/Software Required:
Circuit components, Breadboard, Hook-up wire, Power supply, CRO, DSO,Function generator
Recommended Book: Laboratory Manual for Electronic Devices and Circuits, 4th Ed., David
Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Semester: III Subject: Electric Circuits Laboratory Code: 324363(24) Total Lab Periods:                     36 Batch Size: 30 Maximum Marks: 40 Minimum Marks: 20
List of Experiments: (At leastTen experiments are to be performed by each student)
1. To plot voltage vs resistance characteristics of Incandescent lamp. 2. To calculate the value of resistor using color coding and verify it through measurement. 3. To study the different functions of a Analog/Digital multimeter 4. To verify Superposition theorem for DC/AC Circuits. 5. To verify Thevenins theorem for DC/AC Circuits. 6. To verify Norton’s theorem for DC/AC Circuits. 7. To verify Reciprocity theorem for DC/AC Circuits. 8. To verify Millman’s theorem for DC/AC Circuits. 9. To connect a tube light and study its min. operating voltage, nature of current, power and power factor. 10. To Measure Q Factor of  Series RLC Circuit 11. To Measure Q Factor of  Parallel RLC Circuit 12. To verify the voltage and current relation in star and delta connected three phase system. 13. To verify the effect of three phase unbalanced star connected system. 14. To measure three phase power using Two-watt meter method.
Equipment/Machines/Instruments/Tools/Software Required:
Voltmeter, ammeter, Wattmeter,  Power factor meter,  Resistors, Capacitors, Lamp load, DC supply, Three-phase autotransformer, Multimeter, Simulation tools like MATLAB,PSIM, MULTISIM
Recommended Book: 1. Experiments in basic electrical engineering, S.K.Bhattacharya. 2. Basic shop practical, Mehta & Gupta 3. Practical in electrical engineering, Dr. N.K.Jain
Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Semester: III Subject: Electrical Workshop Laboratory Code: 324364(24) Total Lab Periods:                     36 Batch Size: 30 Maximum Marks: 40 Minimum Marks: 20
List of Experiments: (At leastTen experiments are to be performed by each student) 1. Hands on training of all major tools / Accessories used in electrical workshop. (symbols& abbreviations, Safety instructions are also to be explained during first visit to lab.) 2. Preparation of Test Lamp by the student (Single bulb for single phase test and two lamp in series to test three phase supply), then test the supply in distribution Board / panel on either side of MCB in ON & OFF condition. Test line cord for continuity with test lamp / multimeter. Testing for blown fuse. Replacing the fuse wire with appropriate fuse wire / HRC fuses of  different rating 1A, 5A, 15A, 32 A, 63A and higher ratings. 3. Replace the old element for heater, kettle, non–automatic electronic iron, room heaters etc., with a new one. And test the appliance to ensure proper functioning and safety against shock. 4. Dismantle and reassemble an electric iron, heater, kettle, room heater, toaster, hair dryer, mixie etc. (Minimum 4 appliances) 5. Install a ceiling fan and the regulator. (Group of Two/ Three student may perform the task but each student should practice to connect the wires in ceiling rose.) 6. Check a fluorescent lamp, choke, starter and install it. (About 5 defective tube-light set are to be provided with different type of faults. Student must be able to identify the fault and troubleshoot it.) 7. Understand the different system of wiring used for domestic installation i.e. batten, cleat, casing-caping and conduit wirings and Preparation of one extension board with two sockets, switches and Fuse with indicator. Student must cut slots in Hylam sheet and fix the switches/ sockets / fuse etc and make all necessary connection and fix it on wooden board to ensure safety. Readymade assembly should not be used. (For this particular experiment materials (sheet / switches/ sockets / fuse/ wooden board etc) are to be brought by student and tools will be provided by the Institute. It must be shown to external examiner at the time of practical examination and will be returned back to student. 8. Preparation of PCB as per given layout: a) Artwork & printing of a simple PCB. (b) Etching & drilling of PCB., Insert the components, Solder the components, Taking the input and output leads, Test the assembled circuit. Tell the resistance value by seeing the colour coded resister and verify with the multimeter. Skill development in Soldering and de-soldering techniques. 9. Fabrication of DC regulated power supply. 10. Removal of insulation and fixing of various types of lugs in wire / cable using Crimping tool. 11. Preparation of various types of joints for flexible conductor and ACSR Conductor 12. Fixing of ACSR Conductor on Pin type insulator. 13. Assemble and test rectifier circuits – half wave, full wave & bridge rectifier and test the input /output waveform on CRO. 14. To  provide service connection for industrial installation (3 phase- 4 Wire) 15. Visit to nearby leading Motor Rewinding workshop and observing various repairing and testing activities).
Equipment/Machines/Instruments/Tools/Software Required:
Electric Heater, Electric Iron,  Electric Kettle, Ceiling Fan, Table Fan, Washing Machine, Automatic Iron, Cooking Range, Storage Heater, Wet Grinder, Connector, 6”, Screw Driver 8” 10”, 12”, Cutting Pliers 6”, 8”, Neon Tester, Heavy Duty Screw Driver10”, 12”, Nose Pliers 6”, Soldering iron, Multimeter, Tri Square 30 cm, Fermer chisel 14cm,20cm, 25cm, Pocker 15cm, Power drilling Machine 6 mm, Hacksaw 30 cm, Wire shipper 10 cm, Measuring tape 5 meters, Standard Wire Gauge, CRO, PCB Preparation set, Hand Crimping Tool.
Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand Technical University, Bhilai
Name of program: Bachelor of Engineering                                 Branch: Electrical Engineering Semester: III Subject: Value Education Code: 324365(46) No. Of Periods:                     2 Periods/Week   Total Tutorial Periods: NIL Maximum Marks: 40 Minimum Marks: 24 Course Objectives:
1. This course is designed to provide the importance of education with why, what & how. 2. To impart students with an understanding of fundamental humanitarian viewpoint and its outcomes. 3. To provide the knowledge about whole existence and its impact on values. 4. To bring the awareness about life long exercise so that they can fulfill their responsibility towards themselves, the family, the society, the planet.
UNIT- I Aim of Education and Necessity for Value Education: Education in values/wisdom/etc and education in traits/technologies/etc as the two fundamental strands of education; Answer to the frequently asked questions such as “Why to do studies”, “What studies to do in overall”, “How to do studies in a proper way”, “How to think systematically and talk systematically”
UNIT-II Humanitarian Viewpoint and Basic Human Objective: Meaning and concept of happiness, Need for a fundamental viewpoint to judge things in all cases of human concerns, Proposal of the natural path of humanitarian coexistentialism; Consciousness development and its expression; Fundamental want of sustainable happiness in human being; Understanding the distinct activities and needs of self (I) and body in human being; Fundamental goal of human being; Sustainable-solution in individual (At the place of delusion); Sustainable-prosperity in family (At the place of poverty); Sustainable-cooperation in society (At the place of competition); Sustainable-coexistence in planet (At the place of struggle)
UNIT- III Elements of Holistic and Systematic Perspective: Need for study of fundamental information categories to develop holistic perspective; Particular-time actions and general-time laws; Need for fundamental information sequence to develop systematic perspective, Some examples for systematic study sequence
UNIT-IV Elements of Society-friendly and Environment-friendly Goals: Elements of Knowledge of whole existence; Elements of Knowledge of human being; Elements of fundamental Values and Wisdom; Value spectrum with reference to general relationships and particular relationships of the objects in nature; Elements of History and Contemporarity used to set current goals; Elements of Sciences and Techniques to formulate methods to achieve goals; Elements of Motoricity and Mattericity to make actions to execute the methods
UNIT-V Lifelong Exercise for All-round Sustainability: Collecting information for sustainability issues; Motivating people towards sustainable life-style; Ability to identify and develop appropriate technologies and management patterns for society-friendly and environment-friendly systems for production /protection/ utilization/ experimentation ; Ability to establish and execute the fundamental five-fold system in order to ensure sustainable peace-and-prosperity worldwide.
Text Books:
Value Education for Consciousness Development by Dr P B Deshmukh, Radha K Iyer, and Deepak K Kaushik (2nd Edition, 2012, ISBN: 978-81-924034-0-3)
Reference Books: 1. International Research Handbook on Values Education and Student Wellbeing by Terence Lovat, Ron Toomey, Neville Clement (Eds.), Springer 2010, ISBN: 978-90481-86747 2. Values Education and Lifelong Learning: Principles, Policies, Programmes by David N Aspin and Judith D Chapman (Eds.); Springer 2007, ISBN: 978-1-4020-6183-7 3. Fundamentals of Ethics for Scientists and Engineers by E G Seebaur and Robert L Berry, 2000, Oxford University Press